[Music]
yeah really really looking forward to
this conversation I find it quite
extraordinary that Douglas and Jamie
haven't spoken before certainly not
recorded don't if they have any secret
chats in the last few days they haven't
told me about but so I'm just going to
do a very quick introduction and as Ali
said that the format of this will be
Jamie will speak for about ten minutes
to introduce the topic then Douglas will
speak for about ten minutes to introduce
the topic then we'll bring in the
unhandled question that we've already
worked on and that will be an
opportunity to go away and work on an
answer which we'll bring in later on in
the session after Douglas and Jamie have
dialogue with each other for a bit so
yeah there's so many similarities
between Douglas and Jamie's work and I'd
say that they're two of the the most
interesting and significant cultural
historians on the intersection of
psychedelic culture Tek and the sort of
the mainstream culture at large so Jamie
is a longtime friend of the channel and
he's the author of I'd say the main
guide modern guide to transformational
culture and flow stealing fire the
creator of the flow Genome Project and
he's I think we've done about eight or
nine films I think with Jamie now
ranging from the pitfalls of psychedelic
culture to sort of big transformative
narratives example EMAP thinker and I
really appreciate how he brings together
this sort of really intellectual depth
with an embodied transformational part
with a real sense of integrity and so
Jamie the topic here is building team
human and it's one thing to build team
human when we've got a lot of things
working for us it's quite another thing
now to be looking to build team human or
as you've talked about homegrown humans
when it seems that everything is kind of
falling apart at the same time
you like to frame how you how you see
this hello everybody yeah I'm happy to
and I think what I'd love to do is
anticipate in the conversation
we'll all get to have together after
Doug has also jumped in as we get to
kind of frame this I think the highest
level question that we've kicked around
together is like how do we get to a
place of heightened coherence and
coordination how do how are we at our
best when everything around us appears
to be at its worst so that's the inquiry
for our for our time together this
afternoon or evening or wherever we are
but to kick it off I wanted to actually
read an excerpt from the introduction to
the sequel this tingling fire which I am
writing right now is called recapture
the rapture and the reason is because
Doug has already had a direct influence
on this I remember I've been following
Doug's work for probably 15 years or
more and if anybody's not already
familiar with his stuff I would put him
on the short list of considered thinkers
that are both participants in the
emerging edge of culture and also have a
rigorous scholarly and academic
perspective on it so there his passing
and framing of things is exquisite and I
always the bonus following Doug and also
Eric Davis she was either already gone
on or was about to but either way like I
see them in a shared boat which is they
give that they've given me about a sort
of five to ten years sneak peek as to
what's coming around the bend so when
Doug published this piece a couple of
years ago it was so spot-on with the
work I was doing was like a fucking a
this is an awesome story I have to
retell it too you know and put it in
context with this bigger question so I'm
just gonna read you guys a couple of
pages from the introduction of this book
that will be coming out next year so in
the summer of 2018 author Douglas
rushkoff
throwing rocks to the Google bus named
one of the world's most influential
intellectuals by MIT wrote what amounted
to an update on Evan Osnos his New
Yorker essay from the year before and in
less than 18 months we'd moved from the
hypothetical to the nearly unthinkable
rushkoff received an invitation to
address a bunch of Wall Street financier
Zahn the future of technology a topic
that he had spent his entire career
tracking and while he usually turned
down
kinds of cushy speaking engagements he
was a founder of the cyberpunk movement
back in the 90s after all he admitted
that it was by far the largest fee I had
ever been offered for a talk about half
of my annual professor salary so he
swallowed his disdain did what most
reasonable people would and took the gig
rushkoff showed up on the appointed day
in what he assumed was the green room
the backstage place where speakers and
hosts usually congregate during
conferences five impeccably dressed men
sat down and introduced themselves
slowly rushkoff realized this wasn't the
green room and there was no stage there
was no auditorium full of traders
waiting to hear him talk either these
five men were his audience at first they
asked him a few easy icebreaker
questions what was the deal with
blockchain and cryptocurrencies how far
off did he think quantum computing was
can Google really upload ray kurzweil
mind to the cloud Alaska or nerds the or
New Zealand to escape global warming but
then came the real question the one
those five Titans of Wall Street had
paid north of fifty thousand dollars an
hour to learn how do I maintain
authority over my security force after
the event
that sentence requires some unpacking
let's start at the end and work
backwards the event that was their
euphemism rushkoff explains for the
environmental collapse social unrest
nuclear explosion unstoppable virus
or mr. robot hack that takes everything
down by this point discussing debating
or wondering about future scenarios had
given way for these men to a chillingly
simple placeholder needing no modifiers
or further explanation simply the event
and while these men may not have been
willing to bet on which particular
Domino would fall first and spark a
chain reaction that they would all
topple soon after seems self-evident in
their analysis a fixed constant in a
more complex equation they were still
trying to solve next the verb maintain
Authority carries the distinct
implication that a Authority might be
challenged or questioned in the near
future and be that those five men had it
and intended to hold on to it
finally the object of that action the
noun my security force not my personal
assistant
not even my body man Butler or team my
security force unvarnished plural even
without an S and judging by the urgency
of their $64,000 question on how to
control that group after the event
possibly mercenary for the remainder of
their allotted hour together those hedge
fund managers laid down a few more of
their cards to rushkoff how would they
pay their paramilitary if the economic
system collapsed in paper and digital
currency became worthless how would they
prevent a Lord of the Flies style coup
once things went pear-shaped with secret
combination locks on food supplies web
how about shock collars or AI robots
that's when it hit me rush cuffs said at
least as far as these gentlemen were
concerned this was a talk about the
future of technology taking their cue
from Elon Musk colonizing Mars Peter
Thiel reversing the aging process or Ray
Kurzweil applied the uploading his mind
into a supercomputer they were preparing
for a digital future that had a whole
lot less to do with making the world a
better place than it did with
transcending the human condition
altogether and insulating themselves
from a very real and present danger of
climate change rising sea levels mass
migrations global pandemics nativist
panic and resource depletion for them
the future of technology is really about
just one thing escape
to his credit rushkoff challenged their
assumptions in response to their blunt
questions he answered that the best way
to maintain the loyalty of their private
security force was to start treating
them really well like family starting
now and to not stop there echoing paypal
founder max legend he suggested they do
the same in all their current businesses
on this side of the event the more
effectively they could do that he
suggested the greater the odds we could
all keep the wheels on civilization in
the first place they were amused by my
optimism but they didn't really buy it
rushkoff admits they were not interested
in how to avoid a calamity they're
convinced we are too far gone for all
their wealth and power they don't
believe they can affect the future they
are simply accepting the darkest of all
scenarios and then bringing whatever
money and technology they can employ to
insulate themselves especially if they
can't get a seat on the rocket to Mars
the result will be less a continuation
of the human diaspora than a lifeboat
for the elite rapturous --tz-- every
last one of them so while it's tempting
to marginalize those who embrace rapture
ideologies to think they only show up
preaching fire and brimstone or wired up
to suicide vests the stark reality is
they're all around us wearing black mock
turtleneck sand fleece vests chatting on
iPhones speaking at Ted and Davos tuning
into doomsday preppers on cable TV so a
huge hat tip Doug awesome and thank you
and B I just want to kind of conclude
this with the definitions I think we all
need to become n times literate so to do
that I want to kind of introduce and
define three key terms that typically
get mumbled and jumbled and lumped
together which is the rapture Armageddon
and the apocalypse so I just mentioned
rapture ideologies there and I want to
define how the working all ends that
I've been using for that which is that
rapture ideologies again whether its
traditional and fundamentalist or
whether it's techno utopian
sher actually under the hood for
unifying characteristics it's that the
world is fucked there's an inflection
point coming soon me and mine come up
roses on the other side of that
inflection point therefore let's pin it
and get there as fast as possible and
never mind the collateral damage now the
problem with rapture ideologies is I'm
as you can imagine is they're all one
percenter solutions right and whether
that's the morally virtuous or the saved
whether that's the billionaires with the
ticket to ride whatever the grouping is
right it emits and excludes 99% of us so
the question here is how as the world is
being hijacked and this is Yeats 101
right from the second coming the best
lack all conviction he wrote while the
worst are filled with passionate
intensity so how do we recapture the
narrative around the rapture and how do
we insist on all of us or none of us
solutions because no matter how tempting
a rapture ideology may be and it could
be blocking it could be the psychedelic
Renaissance right you name it right
where it wears we are susceptible to
them all and John Gray at the London
School of Economics it has made a
powerful case that was a book black mass
and the death of utopia where he argues
that all of these including communism
including all of these things are alpha
and omega judeo-christian exit
strategies so how do we make a deep and
profound commitment all of us or none of
us and recapture both the upper case
rapture right the end of time and also
our lower case rapture right our
passionate conviction so that's the
first thing we need to recapture the
rapture but the next is the apocalypse
right and I think I already heard this
in Jordan and Nora and John's talk this
morning which is you know apocalyptic
as' from the Greek literally means the
revealing or the unveiling so while we
want to reclaim the rapture and say not
so far as one percenters okay those are
all sociopathic solutions to a
collective problem we need to actually
accelerate and
bring about the apocalypse the unveiling
so that we can see clearly right and the
final one is Armageddon
um again this actually the endtime
battle this is this is Sauron in Mordor
this is the Battle of five armies this
is where it all goes down so the
question here is how can we recapture
the rapture how can we hasten the
apocalypse and how can we forestall
Armageddon for as long as possible and I
would propose that the solution is the
thing we're here to talk about today
which is all of us coming together in a
vitalized connected courageous team
human so with that
Doug would love to pass her on over to
you right thanks Jamie
that was a I mean you've done my job for
me of a wonderful introduction to dr.
Doug already
I will recap a little bit of what you
said beautifully laid out Jamie Douglas
as Jamie said you've been named as one
of the top 10 most influential
intellectuals by MIT you're the author
of many books including future thought
shock and throwing rocks at the Google
bus you touch you coined terms like
viral media and your most recent book
teen human was a real you described as a
mic drop moment of how do we how do we
recapture these human values from the
big tech companies having sort of
tracked them from the early kind of
utopian Silicon Valley days into a quite
sort of what we might call a dystopian
present and I'd only met you a few times
dope I've really appreciated your you're
a real ambassador for Team human with
your authenticity and earnestness of
inquiry so I'm really looking forward to
to seeing you and Jamie and dialogue
with each other would you like to do
your quick intro and then we'll get into
the unpack uestion yeah I mean lately
I've been I've been questioning my own
identity is a so-called progressive and
the whole notion of progress I mean in
some ways it might be it might be Jewish
guilt talking
but the the the judeo-christian
tradition was to really take a circular
civilization and make it linear you know
with the invention of text we had the
ability to write history and the ability
to write contracts into the future and
it was a beautiful thing and we decided
once we could write things down the
first thing we did was we wrote down the
law we wrote down ethics we thought we
would use writing to make this year
better than last year and next year
better than this year and we move from a
circular understanding of the world in
an indigenous understanding of the world
as a series of cycles to we're gonna
actually get somewhere you know the Jews
we're gonna bring on Moshe you know
there there is a God one God probably a
guy up there somewhere and yes God is
all-powerful and the reason why the
world isn't perfect yet is because
there's this thing called linear time
and once the story unfolds we'll get to
that we'll get to that perfect moment so
let's all keep working eyes on the prize
you know that pedal-to-the-metal ends
justifies the means
arm and arm we're gonna vanquish
everyone who resists us until we get to
that that promised wonderful place and
you know that's what got us in this mess
no no that's what got us into the into
the Industrial Age and now into what
I've been calling digital industrialism
that were applying digital technology to
this scaled Industrial Age exponential
market-based you know universal solution
and where I get concerned is when those
of us who see the fallacy of that
approach when we adopt some of the same
language how are we going to unite as a
planet all the people and figure to take
down global capitalism you know how are
we going to to create this scaled
ghullam to
fight the institutional the
institutional evil out there so that we
look for scaled universal solutions to
these scaled Universal problems when I'm
coming to believe that the answer is not
scaled Universal Global Solutions at all
but extremely particular local highly
highly individual and distributed
solutions that that the response to
globalism is not a universal revolution
but a highly local thing you know the
the anything Universal as far as I'm
concerned anything Universal is is
highly abstracted and divorced from on
the ground reality and the kinds of
solutions we need are going to be real
tiny ones ones that we probably get no
credit for ones that you know there's
not going to be a book title it's it's
it's a different approach it's not
saying everything is fine the way it is
I'm not saying that there's a lot of
problems in the world but the way the
way out is is not necessarily by
erecting something equal and opposite to
- to the problem that the problem that
we're seeing now I was I was watching a
television last night the the the police
strategy in Minneapolis versus the
police strategies in Atlanta and Atlanta
they had all the fires going off and the
police were making ancient Greek phalanx
formations - you know to hold the line
and in Minneapolis the police and
National Guard they just vanished they
just they were nowhere and eventually
it's like the people were marching and
eventually it was like how could you
have anything but a peaceful protest
when there's no resistance to you when
they actually when they when they left
and on a certain level not that we can
ignore oppression no we can't but but
I'm I'm thinking the way we we we take
back reality is by taking back the land
and
our time and our power and our value and
our and our exchange we very locally and
interpersonally you know the the the one
I one regret I have in calling team
human team human is that the most common
email I get is how do I join how do I
join team human and I'm like dude it's
almost always a guy dude you're already
on Team human you know you're you're one
of us I was like well where do I go then
how do I you know I think go to your own
town your own school board your own land
Zoning Commission your own that the way
that the way to do this is going to be
scaled to the human body not to the
abstract Universal organization or
institution that we long for to fight to
fight this battle to fight this battle
for us it sounds like a cop-out but it's
actually harder to do moment to moment
eyeball to eyeball choice to choice in
your community and I think that those
will they won't they won't scale up as
such but they will they will ripple they
will create a different different
experience of reality for so many of us
you know the the problem with the
billionaires was and and I wrote about
it in that piece too was it what they're
trying to do is to earn enough money to
insulate themselves from the reality
they're creating by earning money in
that way you know they're trying to
build a car that drives fast enough that
they can escape from their own exhaust
and what they've realized is it's
impossible that they're coming for us
that I can't insulate anymore that this
is going to blow so they're looking for
you know the the bomb shelter it doesn't
work and I'm looking toward the opposite
how can we individually moment-by-moment
small choice by small choice make the
world a place that we don't need to
insulate ourselves from it that we don't
need to look towards this future day
when everything will be okay to decide
right
this is fucking it right now this where
we're living it there's nowhere to go so
what do you do then what do you do if
this is really it all you can do is
change your behavior your approaches to
the way things are and and for me that's
become that's become the solution I'm
kind of going offline in some ways
because that's why I called team human a
mic drop it's kind of like done you know
I've said more than anybody should
should be allowed to say in in one
lifetime you know so so move on and just
be a nice person now thanks Douglas
well I hope we get at least another hour
out of you before you decide to drop the
mic for good so Douglas and Jane even
working on a question how do we build
team human in a post pandemic world so
yeah so for me to to unpack that
question and by the way I share it I
mean this morning I woke up with a heavy
heart and I'm like man what's the
fucking point you know they want on
earth can we possibly say that can begin
to wrap our heads around any of this
stark raving dumpster fire of other
world and clever thinking thoughts are
clearly insufficient so just to to fully
emphasize that whole I mean it's a total
hackneyed cliche of the think globally
act locally but the flip side of it is
is it's actually highly pragmatic
because if we lose basic communal basic
food security physical security you know
connectivity with our neighbors all
these kinds of things we just go down
through Maslow's you know floorboards
and the most aspirational goals for
collective coherence or whatever you
want to call it simply it's just an
elective option we don't get to play and
so the idea of sort of dusting off
communal community and communal support
and resiliency and self responsibility
does feel an essential part because like
we can't control it all we can't make
sure of governance and politics and
macroeconomics and multinational
corporations to content all that on it
done
but unless we look after ourselves and
get sorted there first at the personal
at the familial and at the community
level then we don't stand a chance of
playing any of the other games so I did
see somebody in there saying as Doug you
were commenting of like oh this sounds
like jordan Peterson's clean your room
but just with it you know a more liberal
bent and and I would actually say sort
of kind of but it's not about personal
morality in this case it's about
connectivity viability and antifragility
and those things I was just saying hey
absolutely let's get on that because we
are atomized fractured rash like hiker
individualist consumers zoo monkeys
right now and we want to break out of
that and get back to like homegrown
human team human requires responsible
self-reliant folks to make it up right I
mean if things can grow by distributing
outward and laterally rather than coming
up with a great new top-down solution
you know where what the thing that
always gets me most nervous when I'm
with a group of great activists is when
they're saying okay how do we get people
to anything it's like once you're trying
to get people to do something then we're
back you know figuring out how to do
propaganda or or social control of one
sort or another and second how dare I be
the one who wants to get someone else to
do something else it's what I'm looking
at now is whether or not sort of the
rapture that you're describing or the
the the you know the apocalypse without
the Armageddon whether that can be a a
gentle unfolding of what is here rather
than reaching towards you know we don't
reach or strive towards apocalypse we
you know when you think about you know
the Buddha or anybody who reaches a some
kind of awakening it's like oh you know
it's not ah you know it's really it's
not the this this very Western quest for
if we could only get there and the other
thing I'm wondering is as our job
changed from I mean this is a very silly
way of thinking about it but we go just
to go maybe but as our job changed from
like saving the world to doing
palliative care
and what would the difference look like
you know pal you know it for to help
everybody contend with the probable end
of our civilization is we go through a
mourning period and kind of and a slow
how can we be kind kindest about it how
can we have the least amount of pain
going into the destruction of the
civilization and hopefully its
replacement with something else or are
we trying to keep this thing is it about
keeping this thing going and then what's
the difference between what those even
what those even look like you know so
it's am almost wondering like is giving
up really such a problem if giving up
just means okay you know we're all gonna
die but let's be as nice to each other
let's make it as painless as possible
let's you know help people experience as
much meaning and connection and you know
and then maybe we'll surprise ourselves
and not Act not die after all yeah and
you're kind of you know you're nudging
into like gem Bendele territory and
right at everything from deep adaptation
to dark mountain to all this kind of
stuff right and I and I'm I wrestled
with that I mean personally I think I am
still nonetheless like irreducibly some
form of like rage against the dying of
the light
thank you I'm going to choose I'm either
gonna go down surfing or go down
swinging you know like it's one or the
other so I guess a maybe of both end
we'll see ran these the made really
where I'm hanging all my hope at this
point is not in the passivity of
palliative care right but is in the
agency of realizing the time for
cherished outcomes has passed but you
know in st. Paul 101 like that it's time
to set aside childish things
mm-hmm and now an imminent you know not
drifted on this with David in the past
but like the notion of what Martin
Luther King called soul force what
Gandhi called satyagraha like that
asymmetrical amplifier of human courage
right which sends shockwaves through
time and space and his
if we can all do normally it's been it's
been one it's been ten people it might
have even been the nominal 300 of
Leonidas and the Spartans right but it's
never it's they're always been tiny
pockets of that you know and it is
shaped the course of civilization so can
we get to that and that is the
reconciliation of the paradox of like
we're stuffed and there's no way out so
let's make up right let's sing our war
song or our love song and that's the
band plays on on the Titanic right I
mean we know those poor little those
four bastards right and they're like
women and children first captain goes
down with his ship this doesn't end well
for me personally
however therefore I am free to do the
only thing that is mine and cannot be
taken away which is which is make up and
that redemptive capacity that's the one
I'm all I'm a home black that is lost
bet and hope and and ways to do it right
the idea of radically initiating
ourselves and each other into and
someone else in the chat said what about
that Kairos Chronos thing that Jordan
was riffing on like being on that and
that idea of like if we can come to a
Gnostic embodied initiatory knowing of
the nature of things right and at the
same time not piece out of of Chronos of
clock time and be fully embodied here
what transformative potential might that
hold for us so that's the one that at
least loosely gets me out of bed in the
morning some days are a knowledge but I
keep coming back to you know yeah and
that's you know and it's holding on to
the you the parent got a paradoxical
paradoxical nature of human existence
you know it's not a circle or line it's
both you know it's not male or female
it's both it's not progress or or stasis
it's both it's not Kairos or Chronos
again it's both but you know both both
in balance somehow you know and that's a
it's tough you know it's a tough one and
and right now the most of the critique
that I get
is from people who believe that we're
already so far gone that the only way
out is through so the topsoil will never
be replenished there's what do we think
there's 30 harvests left or something in
in global topsoil unless there was some
radical transformation in our
permaculture approaches and they'll say
to that well that's the reason we need
Monsanto all the more pedal to the metal
we've got a you know develop more
technologies more industry more
capitalism and more growth is the only
way you know they were to keep this
thing going and I had I hadn't heard
that cherry fact thanks Doug it's
alright let's just add that one to the
list yeah yeah well 30 years is so far
that's so far in the future no yeah well
I mean I'm we we are I think we can
continue happily exploring this just
want to check in yeah alley how's the
questioning going if there's a bit more
yeah we were going to give you a few
more minutes and then come to we've got
a list of questions answers coming up
coming up but if you guys want to want
to riff for another 5-10 and then we'll
yeah I mean I mean just to go back to
you to John Gray a fellow I mentioned he
was taught you know who's cautioning
against that the perils of utopian
thinking of any stripe right and his you
know he made that great observation that
you know even communism is still
Christianity with a different the
judeo-christian alpha-omega with a
different skin you just strip out sky
god but you have the proletariat living
in sin and then the inflection point and
happily ever after in most happily ever
after stories are so a seductive and be
pernicious because the moment the ends
is literally heaven on earth then the
means are always justified to get here
and that's how you get Che Guevara
turning from you know sexy motorbiking
doctor guy to like cold-blooded killer
right and like that we've seen that
movie and so one of the things he he
introduced a term I hadn't even heard of
before which was agonistic liberalism
right in the true sort of post
enlightenment
idea of like we're not ever gonna get to
singing Kumbaya out of a single hymn
book nor should we even try that's part
of the problem the idea of agonistic
liberalism is we want to preserve the
the capacity for the back-and-forth for
the for the vigorous debate between you
know true again you know enlightenment
liberalism and conservatism and then
throw in any other hism schisms and the
idea that what we're fighting for is not
our preferred outcome or our vision of
utopia what we're fighting for is
basically the infinite game and the
ability for us all to keep playing it at
for as long as possible as generatively
as possible to include as many people as
possible and that honestly does feel at
risk right now it feels like on both
sides of the political spectrum you've
got you the the Boogaloo folks I don't
know if anybody's tracking this but like
the far out right who are literally
egging on Civil War like they're banking
on a second civil war like that is those
are death eaters that's like let's just
smash this whole fucking thing to the
ground and you have in the most extreme
aspects of the left
let's dismantle Western civilization
patriot and patriarchy so on both sides
of the political spectrum you have folks
advocating for for the first time in a
century the finite game winning and
blowing up the infinite game of the
Enlightenment experiment so for any of
us that are agnostic and/or humanistic I
think that's the that's the matter
that's the meta conflict that we're
looking at culturally right now and
right we as all of these eschaton like
things do is they make strange
bedfellows and the fact of like the most
militant SJW is actually on the same
team as the 4chan troll in cell and
you're like wait a second how is this
happening and there's that idea that
we're sort of entering the inter twin
hilarity not the singularity and as we
go down the drain pipe of Kairos right
and Chronos like everybody's mythologies
is this the matrix is the Star Wars this
is the evil empire the good geyser is
that the next 2020 election campaign
like I can tell and I can't tell whether
I'm reading revelation or I'm reading
Isis's endgame or I'm reading Hollywood
and sci-fi
and it's gonna make really strange
bedfellow yeah it's interesting the the
decline of the Star Wars franchise
really it tracks what you're talking
about
you know when George Lucas was doing
Star Wars he really meant you don't
really know is the is the Jedi
knighthood corrupt are they the bad guys
as he was trying to say in the second
second three movies maybe who's really
is good what if Luke had joined with his
father to run the universe could they
have yin-yang dit together you know
there were the questions now I mean all
Star Wars there's just bad guys right
bad guys that you kill with with ray
guns so they really did they lost it
that the question is whether the
Enlightenment experiment system maybe
this is just history is whether the
enlightened experiment was just so
flawed that it was based in the kind of
reductionist empirical logic of folks
like Francis Bacon that it was so much
about these kind of platonic ideals it
was so separate from women and people of
color and and and the ground that you
know that that it was incapable you know
that it just moved you to the other
stuff you're talking about it moved to
Hegel and and Marx and Heidegger and all
that stuff it was so it was so it became
so idealized and disconnected from just
what what real experience is you know it
feels I mean not to say that the people
trying to help to save the world or the
problem but in some ways we are we at
least are trying to save it in a way
that makes people happy as opposed to
save it in a way that all black people
are gone or all women are slaves or
whatever these other visions of reality
are but you know I'm I'm trying to kind
of unwind from you know my own
projection of how I want things to be
you know and it's it's a lot of what you
were talking about a lot of what you
were criticizing before reminded me of
when I used to speak with Terence
Mckenna and I would get really mad at
him because I would say look you're
acting like only people who have had the
DMT experience are gonna make it through
the bottleneck at the end of time you
know it's like you better hop on board
and have that so you know how to and I'm
like no it's not going to work George
Bush has to come with us it
like all-or-none they were one one
organism and he's like I'm sorry Douglas
but it's just not gonna work that way
you know you know and and so we our side
such as such as we are that the the
brilliant well-meaning counterculture
can become just as guilty like you say
of of the exclusive exclusionary
thinking I guess where I'm stuck is uh
and maybe it's a fine place to be but
it's almost like any how do how do you
how do you sit with this you know how
it's really it doesn't the hard moment
to sit you know without feeling like
should we be in the streets should we be
shouting shouting a name what projects
should I be developing an alternative
currency should I be you know
volunteering at school and then there's
only so much one person can do so do you
just do the thing do you just you know
it's our it's it's a tough moment for
that well I mean that that that I think
is actually this this all builds
beautifully right because that notion if
we're and again this is a hypothesis
that I'm offering I'm not asserting this
as our shared consensus but if we if we
entertain the idea that actually
cherished outcomes and preferred utopian
destinations are actually part of
structurally part of the problem so we
actually want to commit to some version
of agonistic liberalism and the the
capacity for us to expand and extend the
infinite game for all of us including my
sworn enemies right the whole I'll to
test what you say but defend to the
death your right to say like that
general Jam right if we're committing to
that then the other element is letting a
thousand fires burn like what is the
psycho-spiritual or sort of neuro
anthropological however you want to
frame it equivalent to blockchain what
what we do there is no singular answer
and Jordan and I have actually had this
had this conversation in the midst of
the Cova thing because we were all we
got sucked into that Daniel Jordan and I
on like a whole bunch of team human
projects like very specific PPG's and
epidemiological research and like it was
grinding us into the dirt and I was like
wait a sec I was like I'm an able-bodied
semi capable human but I don't think
this is mine to do and Jordan in classic
Jordan form was like yeah this is you
know instead of talking about Dharma
right or some esoteric concept he's like
this is yours though the work ahead is
and possibly Denson in complex and will
not be sufficiently able to be solved by
any amount of metabolic effort therefore
you should choose what is your Thor's
hammer and like Thor right only like
this infinitely dense an infinitely
heavy and impossible to move unless
you're fucking Thor
so like that invitation for us is let a
thousand fires burn and find your
fucking hammer because there is
something in this world that only you
can do and you need to get clear on it
and do it and then let us crowdsource
the wisdom and the innovation and the
solutions and some will be meta systemic
and some will be grassroots local some
will just be loving and raising a child
or tending a passion of God in your
garden like there will be a billiard
there will be eight billion or even 50
billion innovations and solutions and 99
percent of them will snuff it but among
them somewhere that the flame will
persist and will catch them will Kindle
and that arguably is the best of kind of
the free-market who'd eat those which is
never we've never really got to try the
same way he just said there was only one
Christian and they nailed him to a tree
we've never you know like free the
market free the market of economics free
the market of ideas of innovation of
entrepreneurship and a you know future
proofing but let us all get on it right
I mean once you free the market that's
when the monopolies crumble and you get
the distributed local bottom-up
everybody not everybody necessarily
doing their own thing but you you you
scale solutions appropriately to where
they are rather than force force them
you know and it's also important I mean
I think for a lot of us who are trying
to improve things is to realize that
sometimes small victories are the best
ones you know that I feel like so many
young people are worried about well then
how do I get more followers how do I get
more likes on that how do I grow this
thing how do i you know rather than just
doing something they want to create the
website that aggregates all the people
who are then doing that thing or the
website that aggregates the websites
that are aggregating every
wants to you know become the thing and I
understand if you don't have the million
people on Twitter saying yeah it feels
like it hasn't happened but that's such
a that's such a silly road to go down
you know it's it's it and it's it's so
much easier to find gratification and
and to see the the results of what
you're doing when it's that you know the
smile on the kid that you've talked to
read or you know the the the land that
you've replenished you know it's just
it's so much there there's so much real
work to be done that these sort of
abstracted solutions are I mean that's
why it's tricky for us as two
accomplished white male intellectuals
with published books and all to say oh
don't you know don't stand in front of
crowds with your solution I mean there's
a part of why I've been feeling
hypocritical lately as whatever this is
public intellectual it's part of why I
want to just like be a teacher and and
and help people locally it's not to say
I'm done but it's like it's there there
there's enough other ideas and other
people so I just want to stay somehow
stay in service rather than in whatever
whatever the the opposite is yeah right
so we're gonna throw in the first answer
from the the unmanned or and but if you
could do another Terence Mckenna
impression at some point during the rest
of the talk
Douglas I think everyone would
appreciate that that went down really
well that high-pitch psychedelic wine
yeah it's awesome
so Ali I think the first is rain Revere
yes can you hear me yeah yep well um I I
responded to the question that was posed
by bringing up death and our
relationship with death and really our
relationship with mortality what are
resource constraints if we're not
playing the immortality game anymore I
mean if we don't want to live forever
yeah I think the question is how how how
much are those
game theoretic competitive aspects of
society that we're seeing part of this
conscious and unconscious drive for
immortality and yeah does how important
is a relationship with death and
mortality to be able to widen and not be
seeking that endgame yeah I'd say
absolutely non-negotiable essential so
like I don't think we actually get to
soul force until you've met your maker
until you've actually reconciled with
dying and I share this quote all the
time because it literally guides my life
at this point but as Wendell Berry and
he uses that phrase practice
resurrection so the idea of like you
know in in sports science there's the
notion of like the last mile problem or
conundrum which is how marathoners will
run clockwork five minute miles and then
they'll get inside the stadium and see
the finish tape in their final mile
they'll suddenly run a sub five-minute
mile even though they're exhausted and
you're like what the hell is that and
what it is consistently is some neuro
physiological and psychological offer in
our system that says don't spend it all
you will die and once we know we are
safe then we have extra we have this
reserve tank it's the same way when if
you try and hold your breath underwater
and you think you have to breathe you're
actually only at about 40 percent of
your maximum breath alone but all the
safety buffers are like Mayday Mayday
get a gulp but you're gonna drown so by
some point by hook or crook right either
life and hard knocks or initiatory
deliberate practice like in cultivate
death practices such that like the
samurai idea of like meditate a thousand
ways to die so when you're on the
battlefield you our undivided in your
attention like it feels like we have to
have already reconcile with our
immortality to be able to source and
offer from love in a truant in a truly
like exponentially transformative way so
absolutely reanimate i think i think
that's the non-negotiable one and that
we are
absolutely a death though that culture
we ship our elders off to be cared for
minimum wage by strangers on you know
and our elders are on drugged up and we
poke and prod each other with botulism
toxin and fellows to pretend we're not
aging so like yes 20 percent bring dying
back and make it a central part of our
orientation to how we live yeah I mean I
got I got to deal with death a lot just
from people I know you know dying and
being with them and thinking about it
and then um you know Timothy Leary tried
to do a kind of a design for dying
around around his death and
interestingly he kind of abandoned that
trip as he got close to the end and it
got really serious he was like oh fuck
this I just gonna I got a really deal
with dying here it was it was
interesting to see you know the show is
over I can't do death as a show I'm
actually I'm not gonna freeze my brain
and I'm not doing this I'm gonna deal
with dying and I feel okay about dying
but then I mean what I've been concerned
about is the the death of our
civilization or the death of our species
or the death of life itself and trying
to apply the same understandings of
Resurrection to to that or return or the
the eternal return to civilization and
then I interviewed James Lovelock a few
months ago who's a hundred years old the
Gaia hypothesis guy and he said well
because the Sun is so much hotter now
than it was when life started on earth
back when if we reach the tipping point
and it got too hot for life on Earth and
life on Earth died we no longer have the
conditions for life to start again that
that that he believes that the the
maintenance of the appropriate
temperature for biology as we know it to
exist on this planet is is very it's a
delicate system and it's it's in it's in
danger so then I started to think about
well what if everything dies right what
if life on Earth dies and what if it
turns out that this was the only life in
the universe and it turns out that the
only life in the universe was the
universe's only bit of self-awareness
so what if it's really dying and do we
how do we how do we you know how does
one come to terms with that and it's
just so for me it's again it's so
hopelessly linear it's so different from
the sustainable circular reincarnation
you know imitation of the Gods sort of
myth of eternal return that that that
indigenous people hadn't that I'm trying
to to to you know kind of adopt adopt
myself as a little Western linear person
but I'm trying I feel like even if we're
even if we are gonna go on and it is
gonna be okay
we've got to even as a society as a
civilization we've got to contend we've
got to accept that possibility as well
except that the that you know yes I'm
playing the infinite game but infinity
might not be mine you know we might not
it's it's you play it and keep it going
as long as we can keep that you know
that hacky sack up in the air as long as
we can as a as a species but also accept
that if if we are temporary what what is
what is that then you know and and and
and you know what does that mean for art
for our you know I've been reading 11 us
lately
there's a really interesting guy and he
basically says that all we've really got
is our comportment it's how you can port
yourself is really all that you can all
that you can know how do you engage with
the other and how do you expand you know
Timothy Leary was the one who had the
quote find the others but he meant find
the other cool psychedelic people and
then when I've retrieved find the others
I mean find the others fine
you know the manga hat-wearing scary
people that you don't really think you
like and find the human in them and then
I just met an indigenous man who is like
now the others are the other species
it's not the other you've got way more
you've got everything in common with
that Trump supporter you think you're
different from him
it's like start recognizing the others
that you're trampling on so yeah I'm
playing with that too but it's just
expanding our notions of self and and
supposed other play into the
real misperceptions and fear and fear of
death
which I but I totally agree it's stuff
that it's it's essential I mean Becker
was writing about it and and really he
nailed it right and now so much of our
everything we do all those billionaires
we were talking about they're just
scared to die they're really just scared
to die and they do so much you know
you're absolutely right and when you're
not because the fact is all that
gamification you know as we they showed
when they tried to recreate the
prisoner's dilemma experiments they
never work they never work people never
behave that way they never do
the thing that who was it what was his
name the game theorist they
schizophrenic who uh yeah John Nash you
came up with him and later he said look
I was a paranoid schizophrenic coming up
with these ideas this is not this is not
the normal human response but yeah but
when you are afraid I mean it's
certainly in the big picture more afraid
of death shirt we're gonna we're gonna
we're gonna gather we're not gonna trust
that the mana is coming from heaven the
next day and you know what you get you
get worms yeah I love the the prisoner's
dilemma I think the only people that did
the prisoner's dilemma in that way were
economists because they've been taught
that that's what they were supposed to
have done so we've next up is Gordon
Young you had an answer to the question
yes yeah so the problem posed by the
question is how do we deal with limited
resources or resource constraints and
the the issue with that or one way
around it is recognition that the best
things in life aren't things that that
once we get past a certain level of
resource that the things that we value
we're valuing them for the ability to to
make our lives better but but not
necessarily by making our lives better
in a material sense and so in some ways
it was a an easy answer you know a banal
answer to the question but I think the
part that's
that merits a lot of contemplation is
how do you how do you awaken that
recognition for people especially in
this culture that we're you know in our
Western culture but I don't think it's
our Western industrial information
culture I think it's I think there's a
lot of sort of genetic evolutionary bias
towards individual trying to trying to
get more right how much money is enough
well just a little bit more with John D
Rockefellers answer right sure how much
you know how do you know you're wealthy
enough well when I when I can afford
better toys than my brother-in-law right
well there's there's some pretty innate
forces that drive us towards this
material porosity so the the question I
think that's that's really interesting
is how do we how do we awaken that
recognition individually for ourselves
and for the people around us and the
culture in the you know seven and a half
billion of us that are on this planet I
think you know the the event is coming
unless we do awaken this kind of
recognition and so I think that's where
that where's the growing edge how to how
to propagate that understanding that
there's there's more to life than just
the material I don't have any answers
for it that's but that's that's why I'm
here is to talk about it with other
people so hope that sparked some other
interesting conversation yeah and I mean
you know that is that's the kind of
those are those are the shallow waters
we're all run aground in in the kind of
personal growth and transformation space
right because people are like oh wait
I'm grinding and I'm chasing material
stuff and then either sand deck or
totally or or whatever I drop a
surrogate of any minute I'm like eh
we're all on it screwy and I'm gonna
hold this as long as I possibly can into
wham wham wham and now I'm pulled down
again into my material seeking striving
animal self and my sense is if we want
something to work we have to fully
acknowledge the better angels of our
nature but also the baser animal and we
actually have to meet
both good you can't just go fucking
cross-eyed and pretend you know
hypothermic don't make good poets right
I mean there's just basic hierarchy of
evolutionary biology and code and
competition etc and so my sense would be
is that the like because the question
that we posed which is how do we play
well together when the stakes are high
and there's a ton of in like attempts or
efforts for us to gel together and do
this hard thing and we fragment and we
fragment it feels to me at the top and
we fragment at the bottom so we fragment
with the large number of people that try
to come together on behalf of the bigger
cons and there needs to be some basic
version of hey I mean ubi is a
contemporary expression of it but
basically we find a way to meet
everybody's basic needs so that striving
for competition and advancement and one
up one down relationships is at least
hypothetically off the table now there's
the multipolar trap in game theory which
is if someone's gonna rush to break the
pact then it might as well be me right
and then you get shitty sociopathic
behavior again simply without even
having to have a sociopath in the mix
it's just I suspect someone else might
be therefore I will act to protect my
own interests so I remember in grad
school reading a case study of the 19th
century range Wars in northern New
Mexico
and it was this fascinating story if you
guys don't miss one the Cowboys are like
fencing everything and it was basically
a pitched battle between the Hispanic
sheep herding communities and the Anglo
cattle companies right and and it was
you know the cattle companies were going
around and killing all that killing all
the Hispanic folks and fencing
everything for their cattle super bloody
crazy conflict but what was fascinating
is that in the Hispanic mountain
communities where there was limited
resources this was high alpine not super
lush kinda sketchy was that within those
villages there was explicit social
shaming against individually taking more
than your fair share so there was net
like if one goat herder started
basically trashing the Commons in order
to asymmetrically gather capital right
in the form of a bigger
walk or whatever they were actually
socially shunned and shamed that would
be the kind of thing their mother would
take him aside
don't be an asset what are you doing
right or their friends would maybe
distance them or tease them or something
along those lines and so some version of
a ubi and this could be in an
intentional community this could be in
an urban environment all the way to a
nation-state but some form of that and
then some form of healthy pro-social
shaming which is different than guilt
and I know there's different and
conflicting definitions of this term but
the idea of like guilt is unhealthy
that's me I'm not worthy but shame is I
have transgressed the highest norms of
my society of my in-group and I am
responsible for atoning for them and if
we have that at the base layer is there
a chance for us to an you know to
basically renormalize the Commons and
pro-social behavior so I'll leave it at
that there's also a top-down element
which is how do you take the the most
awake charismatic transmission folks and
how do you get them to play well to go
there which is another nut to crack but
we can come back to it if it pops up
yeah it's hard I mean and and as you
know you know until now the most of the
most of the social shaming is being done
by the the wicked on the good you know
to make us you know shameful about about
you know sex or gender or whatever you
know that we carry around shame and the
truly shameless people the people who do
the shameful stuff are shameless right
now it's not even it's not even it they
don't seem to they don't seem to care
but but I agree you know the the you
know my work has always been about
trying to reveal the underlying
operating systems that people accept is
given conditions of nature but are
actually inventions so central currency
everybody thinks okay money so how are
we gonna get more money to more people
and this and it's like you know and some
of us are challengeable what is money
what kind of money are we using what's
the what are the rules of this money
compared to Alette system or time
dollars or something that doesn't have
interest and have to grow and you know
what if we created money that was that
was optimized for the velocity of of
currency rather than the extraction of
capital and what would that will
like and you go back and you start
reading the moral philosophers like Adam
Smith and John Stuart Mill and you see
that they were actually thinking the way
we are even though they've been become
the patron saints of you know the
economists and neoliberalism you know
they're they no more believed in that
then Darwin believed in in competition
is the only path the only path of
evolution so I'm I'm feeling like the
the the path is the retrieval of really
largely medieval economic mechanisms you
know the the Commons and market monies
and local currencies and let people
experiment with those in you know in
their you know hi small local ways and
then and then hopefully see them see
them expand out
I mean subsidiarity is the answer to the
last two questions in some ways
subsidiarity was a sort of an economic
principle that said no business needs to
should grow no business should grow
larger than it needs to in order to
conduct its business you don't grow for
growth's sake you Joe makes his pizzeria
it serves his community and the next
town gets its own pizzeria and that's
actually more resilient because then if
he runs out of dough he can call Mary in
the next towns that you've got extra
dough I'm running out here it's not it's
not his pizzeria anymore so these these
you know these models these models exist
it's just right now you know when I talk
to you know suppose people in power I
guess are people who seem to be able to
implement some of them on larger scales
they they really don't believe they're
possible there so the the laws of
scarcity based central currency you know
profit capital economics are so embedded
they haven't read their history they
don't even know that these things these
things are possible
you know UB Iwerks out mathematically it
just doesn't work in their understanding
of of how money works so we've got maybe
time for one or two more but Dave pandal
could we get your answer to the question
I was sensing I've had an experience of
a collective awakening that is
enlightenment beyond the individual so
it seems to be if there's a wreck a deep
recognition an embodied recognition of
interdependence on others and the system
and the earth that seems to be a way to
shift consciousness away from purely
preoccupation with survival I'd by that
I mean you were not you're not alone you
know it's the way I've been trying to
sit tell it to people you're not alone
this is a this you know the being human
as a team sport you know and it and and
it's so much easier when you do it but
people are still I don't know when yeah
I'm not a psychologist but you know
there's this there's this terrible twos
phase you know where the child where the
baby realizes it's really separate from
its mother and has the ability to say no
and experiences itself or himself
herself as as a distinct and it's an
important stage for the baby to go
through as distinct then you know
certainly by the time they're adolescent
then they want to reconnect with all
those you know and become one with all
these other with all these other people
and I feel like we've our civilizations
gotten stuck in in that cult of
individuality that we only feel you know
truly alive or truly flourishing if we
are you know somehow manifesting
individually and it's a it's a shame
it's a shame but maybe that's breaking
down you know maybe we're gonna you know
reach and we're gonna reach that
adolescent stage and and start to start
to realize though that there's the
potential for a party here you know I
mean that's part of what you know the
beauty of what the even even in an even
at Burning Man even at you know whatever
gathering whatever weird psychedelic you
know rave that you're at
however commercial and whoever silly and
even if Eric Schmidt comes it doesn't
mean that there's not the possibility
for that that waking up that oh my god
it's so much more fun with other people
and once you get there at least you're
starting on the way you know poor Maslow
you know putting putting
self-actualization at the top of
up at the top of the pyramid you know it
it it created a detour for a lot of us
into this idea of self-improvement and
you know this whole self-help movement
and you go to Esalen and sit in your
little thing and and manifest as as
yourself there's such a it just
dovetailed so easily with the me
generation and and consumerism and
personal empowerment and and then the
cosmas and life extension and my life
life extension not of our plan but life
extension of me and i'm gonna upload my
brain to that computer and it's a it's
it's that's our side getting a little
silly about this stuff too but yeah I
totally agree once you break down the
barrier and realize you're not alone in
this trip that you've been you've been
connected to all these other people the
whole time it becomes I think a little
bit easier to to manifest in some of the
ways that were we're suggesting yeah
yeah and and and then for anybody that
isn't already familiar with Scott Barry
Kaufman Zwick he was a protege of
Seligmann at Penny's now at Columbia I
think he said he's a buddy and he just
published a book called transcen which
is about Maslow's unpublished lost
papers and the fact that the cherry on
top of the pyramid was not actualization
it was transformation meaning in
Maslow's times
servus servus so the fact that we spend
30 or 40 years and the entire boomer
generation went barking off you know to
narcissistic self-indulgence is one
thing and then Dave to your point I mean
yes wouldn't it be nice wouldn't it be
nice Beach Boys right I mean if we all
found that we had unity consciousness
and we were connected to source right
and we could all manifest from there yes
but then the next the next crux is who
the fuck grabs the One Ring of Power
because like it's magic and it's potent
and then the so let's just say let's
just telescope ahead okay yes that's
possible it's reproducible its scalable
and a ship pilot people are doing it all
at once right now and how do we learn to
play together
well once people are actually tapping in
to the mainframe and because because you
know Lord Acton 101 absolute power
corrupts right so
the notion so when I posited that
bottoms up like UB is health and social
shame as a way for us to manage the
excess grasping of game theory drivers
and the positioning in the jockeying and
someone in the comments had mentioned in
addition to that he spanned a
sheepherding social norm there's also
the particularly in the Pacific
Northwest tribes the notion of the
potlatch which is that when I accumulate
wealth I actually accrue status not by
holding it and hoarding it like the
dragon Smaug right but actually by
gifting it and putting the velocity of
wealth back into my society so it's
almost sort of like an indigenous
version of metcalf law like I actually
gained power within the network right by
dis redistributing and reallocating
resources versus hoarding so that's
super neat but the toss down one is is
as or more problematic which is you know
a conversation I think we've all been
having in this you know on rebel wisdom
and elsewhere you know which is why is
it that people that are sourcing from
that place tend as a rule not to play
well with others
yeah and how the hell do we actually
bomb this together and one of it it
feels like because because up until now
the waking up process or the actual
izing process has been largely
individual and catch-as-catch-can so
we're all like apex predators like
Panthers and we all need 400 square
miles of territory you try and put you
know you put a dozen Panthers in a pen
together and it's a shit show you know
versus if you guys saw that documentary
blackfish right about about Orca pods
like they've bigger bigger brains than
we do and then the all the extra folds
are for social coherence so they
literally have anatomically they are
hard-wired to their apex predators to
the Wolves of the sea they're badasses
but some they have figured out how to
play this game and so for me that's the
true missing link and I mean lots of
efforts in the last five years of coming
together with smart brilliant intention
you know like Dhamma holders or whatever
they've all got their super power and
the super heroes cannot get it fucking
done
and so one proposed solution would be
the idea of like can we can we see each
other's light from each other's light
right without getting pushed away from
each other by seeing each other's shadow
or fail ability or humanity and so if
you find as a thought experiment like
who's your 12 like find your dozen and
think about the people that are closest
in your life and think about the
beautiful perfect part of them that is
their expression it could be they're
always the humorous one they're always
the adventuresome one there o is the
emotionally intelligent one this is the
creative harebrained idea when like I
love you fully and wholly for that in
that expression when you're on that you
are perfect right and that's also
because we can love each other out but
then there's also the element of well
hey rather than some of us getting kind
of sort of most of the way there and
whether it's pressure from the
marketplace or Instagram or whatever we
stop fronting that we're all the way
there we actually say what if we
assemble from this dozen that is our
chorus right as bonding it would call it
right our crew that we say we take your
slice of the divine we take your slice
of the divine this is your slice your
slice and we assemble Voltron we
assemble perfected human that is the sum
total and mediated by all of our
relationships which is we express the
agape like I fuckin love you because I
see the perfected in you but none of us
grab the ring that's a non-starter but
between us we can hold the metabolise
perfected human and we can we can
transfer all worship right sacrifice
dedication loyalty to that hologram that
is the one right how they metabolized by
the twelve and can we use that as a way
to precipitate what Tila de Chardin
called the you know the omega point like
the body of Christ to Sheridan said is
the second coming at the end of time
that is all of us as a Macon's right I
don't go to Omega but it's nice I mean I
guess I don't believe the ring actually
has power was super Woody Allen of you
right there but okay good I try it's
better than Terrence in some ways it's
closer to my origins but the the the
ring I look at the ring in a social
construction you know again from Torah
it's like Samuel goes to God and says
everybody wants a king they want a king
everyone else has a king now the Jew
is really they want a king what do I do
and God hate that guys like they'd know
no we don't do Kings it's not what we do
cuz it's about power and all you don't
we don't do that Sam it's like looked at
really and they're not gonna do not
gonna behave they really really want a
king and God says all right pick the
tallest guy pick the tallest guy as if
it's just like it doesn't just pick some
dude you know at that point it was all
dude you should have picked a woman but
but pick the tallest one put the crown
on so they know it's the King the whole
idea is the crown to me the crown is
about the opposite of power but the
crown is saying the only reason why this
person gets to be Kings is they wearing
the crown it's a total social
construction we're gonna pretend like
this guy is something when he's actually
not in order to just administrate what
we're doing and and we've you know we've
fallen into the trap of feeling like our
kings are actually powerful that they've
got that they've got something where you
know I prefer almost the kind of the
revelation and Eyes Wide Shut when
Sydney Pollack basically reveals as the
head of the big secret great Illuminati
cabal that he's just an administrator
you know it's it's just something we got
to do every year it's just you know this
is just that's all they are
they're just administrators but anyway
it's just because when you're talking
about the ring
I wonder but we can empower it certainly
if we focus on on that power we can
invest power in it I believe in magic
you mean I think it'll it'll go there
but if we started to see leadership as
this other as a social construction it'd
be so much easier to deal with yeah well
you can is that it several times today
Doug you've mentioned mostly the most
often a guy when you're kinda talking
about the old you there Krishna store
and you're like often dudes here during
this not in the other and it should have
been a woman so in a and another like
bit of culture architecture it was like
a really healthy thing in addition to
the basic needs met and potentially
pro-social shaming and and building
mechanisms for redistribution of excess
resources and all the kind of pot lash
notion another potential is literally
like the grandmothers council right
because you know Jared Diamond writes
about this in like menopause is very
rare in nature
and is actually an adaptive treatment
and even in the primates broadly and
it's in its Palma it's one of the more
unique things including mating outside
of estrus and this kind of stuff that
humans have and the adaptive reasoning
is that hey grandmother's actually
provide evolutionary advantage by
bestowing wisdom and helping raise the
tribe and the idea that because they're
no longer in the procreation game which
is arguably the root game theory play
because they're outside of that they
have the capacity to hold wisdom for the
collective in a way that virtually no
one else does and so you know the
iroquois council had that they had that
sitting above the war chieftains and the
war chieftains would have to go to the
grandmothers council be like can we go
whack those dudes and they'd be like you
could but if you lose any of our boys
you're gonna have to go back and now
we're in a blood feud like don't fuck it
up so rather than like attrition and
this kind of stuff they had to be
seamless
so like men i would submit a really good
at three things we're good at fighting
stuff fucking stuff and building stuff
but why to fight and who to fuck and
what to build were terrible and so
anchoring that counterbalance right with
where they're council grandmother's
feels like it could be a you know a
relatively shorter path to a bunch of
solves so where we've got about 10
minutes left just a bit less than 10
minutes left so I was gonna give Douglas
and Jamie the opportunity if there's
something that you haven't a question
you have an arm our store something you
wanted to say I'd like to spray
something any you can take this or you
can go with something different just
that with both of your work there's a
similarity
you've both kind of looked at
transformational culture psychedelic
cultures potentially having a lot of the
answers like as a sort of of hope for
culture and you both to some degree I
think come out in a you know in a less
hopeful place I'm interested do you
still have hope for that for that those
tools that that part of culture or not
wherever you
I mean I I have hope in some ways I
think I have more real hope and than I
did before
I just don't have climactic hope you
know I don't have big hope I don't have
spectacle hope I've got you know I've
got small aged hope you know would you
in some ways it's it's I mean I used to
believe with Terrence that you know
we're doing something that or you know
they Chardin that humanity is evolving
to the next phase and just as a you know
water boils and reaches complexity that
humanity is moving to the next fractal
level of awareness but the collective
holographic mind is about to be realized
and then Internet is the trial run and
psychedelics are the lubricant and now
you know you will is Terrence used to
say you will literally be able to see
what I mean and it was the way he talked
about it that we'd go like squid into a
into a virtual psychedelic virtual
reality collective thing and as an
adolescent or a young man I was like
yeah you know let's go there let's reach
it let's find it and I was always a
little questioning even in the first
book Siberia I'm like is this the
Philosopher's Stone or is the
Philosopher's merely stone you know and
I would even back then and my most
idealistic I was open to are they right
is are you serious really you know the
friggin you know Andy Warhol of the 21st
century or is this just a bunch of
people stone what's what's going on and
and I find myself in some ways almost
almost less cynical than I was then
because I'm no longer evaluating whether
Humanity is about to rise from the
chrysalis of matter into pure
consciousness before the weight of
capitalism takes us down and I'm much
more interested in you know these these
tiny relationships between people and
maybe it's fantasy or maybe it's not but
this sense that when I make genuine eye
contact an established rapport with just
one other
person that that is trickling out
whether it's quantum or god or something
else that that is my whole universe at
that moment and it's not it's not
nothing it's not white privilege it's
not it's not a psychedelic fantasy it's
real and it's happening in in my path
you know and that that if that if that
doesn't that mace kale better then that
whatever forty thousand copies of some
book that I've written and have traveled
around you know that that that that is
fine write the book and it's fine and
it's entertainment I just don't know if
the knowledge production and sort of
industrial age spread of all this stuff
is really more meaningful than than that
then that tiny yeah yeah and I mean and
and I think we're very much exploring
same things about sort of you know is it
is the wave is it a particle is it a
hockey stick Redemption curve or is it
an endless yeah a polychronic quantum it
mr. Balaji holds all of them and says
hey reality collapses based on the lens
you lay over it and I think there's my
strong hunch right now is that yes there
is that hockey stick curve but if you
zoom and it feels like we're
accelerating right up the knee of it to
some Omega point but we'll get there and
realize you soon out you're like oh this
was actually just an AA this was just a
piece of what is in fact a full circle
right and it's a full circle on
civilizational rise and fall like
Ozymandias one on one look upon my works
ye mighty or or Charlton Heston in the
Planet of the Apes with you know the
Statue of Liberty buried up to its you
know it buried in sand like we will
realize hey man
bigger civilizations more complex shit
has come and gone both on this little
blue marble and off it and we are all
just wheels within wheels and at the
same time the transformational point
that I make a point I do still feel as
there to which is not that we get to
peace out and it's and it's the the
rapture escape but that we actually get
to become twice born so to reign to your
question about death and mortality like
when we die to ourselves and our
preferences you know and our stories in
this life
and still in this body and we get to be
twice born right as a humdrum human on
Team human then we realize we come back
all the way to exactly what you were
talking about which is the fucking here
and now my family this rocking chair
that garden Ryan and that and the hope
you have that phrase like that whenever
whenever there be the blowhard dude
sitting around the Kiva you know some
some grandmother would be like yeah but
does it grow corn and so we can come
home full circle like Dorothy having
gone on that heroic transformative path
that realized with fresh eyes and for
the first time there is no place like
home and this is it and this is
everything so that the starlight and the
transcendence is is perpetual and
timeless it's it's opposable thumbs and
eight or nine decades to do this human
thing that is the embodied miracle and
both worth fighting for passionately
right and allowing to be what it must
like wit wit where Castaneda like talks
about with Don Juan he says you know he
says this so the Warriors task is to do
what he must knowing it is futile and to
do it anyway
his is the act of controlled folly and
once we once were once we've swallowed
that one then it's all fun and it's all
odd was a fantastic wrap up from you bow
thank you so much for that really free
ranging conversation and for for
bringing it back down to earth at the
end and and it sort of it was back down
to earth and it was cosmic at the same
time so thank you and for the second
Terrence impressions well Douglas you
asked yeah yeah fantastic this was one
of the talks from the rebel wisdom
festival a dozen more films from the
festival are available in our members
area from John Devaki Jordan Hall Nora
Bateson Jamie wheel Douglas rushkoff and
many more
so become a rebel wisdom member and get
access to loads of exclusive films and
join the rebel wisdom community for
cents making calls our wisdom Jim and
more we're also running our online
course again soon since making 101 with
faculty including Daniel Shmack Tim
burger check out the website for more